<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-11-25T23:39:25-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Looking For An Advisor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/looking-for-an-advisor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking For An Advisor" /><published>2018-11-25T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/looking-for-an-advisor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/looking-for-an-advisor.html">&lt;p&gt;Looking for a research advisor in graduate school is scary. You probably don’t know the professors very well yet, and you might not even know what they like to do. They have whole research lives at this point, and understanding what they have done and what they are currenly working on requires reading articles and making a list of professors that &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be doing the kind of research you are interested in. There are so many reasons to continue to procrastinate–but here’s some advice: just start talking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are actually going to read through every professor’s last three papers, then great! Do it this weekend, and start talking next week. But if you don’t get through them this weekend (or don’t even start), then just start talking to people. It’s easy to let a whole term or two pass by while you try to be “prepared” to talk to professors. Getting in early on research, especially in a master’s program, is key to sucess. You’ll learn a lot about your professors just by talking them. And in all honesty, most professors will be delighted you just are interested in their area of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most deparments have a list on their website about the “focus areas” of each professor. Find the top 3-5 professors that are doing something that you might be interested, and email them. If you have a small department, you could even just stop by their office and ask if there is a good time to talk to them about their research in the next week or two. Taking the initiative early on to connect will impress them more than remembering the titles to their last few papers. Once you have the meetings scheduled, that will give you a deadline to do a little background research. Reading the last few papers they authored is fabulous, but reading the abstracts of their last 10 years’ papers is more realistic and actually gives you a better idea of their breadth of work. Professors will often refer to research they worked on 10 or 15 years ago, and if some of their papers are strictly interesting to you, your time is better spent talking to them in person about what their interests are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, don’t let your to-do list get in the way of making real connections. Most professors are kind people that want to talk about their research. If you end up talking to one of the professors that has higher expectations of reading about their research beforehand, they will probably let you know, and then you’ll have a reason to come back after having done that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>aaron</name></author><summary type="html">Looking for a research advisor in graduate school is scary. You probably don’t know the professors very well yet, and you might not even know what they like to do. They have whole research lives at this point, and understanding what they have done and what they are currenly working on requires reading articles and making a list of professors that might be doing the kind of research you are interested in. There are so many reasons to continue to procrastinate–but here’s some advice: just start talking.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Applying To Graduate Schools</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/01/applying-to-graduate-schools.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Applying To Graduate Schools" /><published>2018-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/09/01/applying-to-graduate-schools</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/01/applying-to-graduate-schools.html">&lt;p&gt;Be prepared to be disappointed. Some of the most successful professors I have met told me that they did not get into many of the grad schools they applied to. Personally, I did not get into &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of the PhD programs I applied to the first time around. However, if you’re smart about it, and understand a little about how academia works, then you can downgrade your stress from unbearable to just above annoying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first piece of advice I would offer is that you need to have a backup plan, or be extremely aggressive if you don’t. For me, my backup plan for getting a PhD was to get a master’s degree first, then reapply to PhD programs. This actually worked out really well for me, but I was transitioning from a different field (physics) into economics, so a master’s really had the potential to provide a great transition and give me more time to understand the research. For some, a backup plan might be to just work for another year or two in a related job, or to get a lengthy post-baccalaureate internship. Your backup plan is something that you won’t feel bad about doing, and that has the potential to make you look goo on your second round of graduate applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you are ready for grad school, and you want to get into grad schools…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>aaron</name></author><summary type="html">Be prepared to be disappointed. Some of the most successful professors I have met told me that they did not get into many of the grad schools they applied to. Personally, I did not get into any of the PhD programs I applied to the first time around. However, if you’re smart about it, and understand a little about how academia works, then you can downgrade your stress from unbearable to just above annoying.</summary></entry></feed>